<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Thinking about...</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/thoughts.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2014-08-23T18:58:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Being a developer</title><link href="/career.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-08-23T18:58:00+02:00</published><author><name>ihommmani</name></author><id>tag:,2014-08-23:career.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Being a software developer&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A passion made of interactions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In each serious developper's interview there is always the same classical question.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;What do you like about programming ?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
To be totally honest it wasn't something I have dreamed about being a kid. Nor a teenager for that matters.&lt;br /&gt;
Yet I have always been tied up with computers since my childhood. Doing things and others like hacking public computers to get access to the internet.&lt;br /&gt;
But seing people working in front of their screen all day long wasn't apealing to me.&lt;br /&gt;
Then I discovered a totally different world. Far from what one can expect.&lt;br /&gt;
Unlike the common cliche people think, a true programmer does not spend his entire day motionless and/or silent.
The day is full of interactions. &lt;br /&gt;
In fact, as a programmer, &lt;strong&gt;the more you interact the better&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
Interaction doesn't necessarily means speaking with people. Reading, writing (via social medias, forums, blog articles and others) are also part of the interaction process.&lt;br /&gt;
It is a great source of inspiration and lets you &lt;strong&gt;change your mind, renew your knowledge and share your point of view&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
All in all, it allows you to &lt;strong&gt;change and adapt&lt;/strong&gt;, something important in such line of work.&lt;br /&gt;
Besides, you also have the satisfaction to see things you build working and having a positive impact on others.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A mutating profession&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately for many years programmers were being seen as resources. Someone you give specifications and then ables to translate the needs into lines of code.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Denying in the process his/her ability to think and create&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
Lately big tech companies and movement like &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_craftsmanship," title="craftmanship"&gt;software craftmanship&lt;/a&gt; emerged. It's an important step in the recognition of developer's carreer as a prestigious one. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Programmer is not a tool or a resource anymore, but someone you have to rely on&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
Someone able to renew the way you think your business. Someone with the abilities to make business happen. Someone who has talent for inovation.&lt;br /&gt;
Reality reminds these simple facts every days:&lt;br /&gt;
- Behind the success of such companies like Google, Facebook and others there are developers&lt;br /&gt;
- Behind all these devices which make your life simpler, there are developers&lt;br /&gt;
- Behind the video games you play, there are developers  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Programmers who thought and built a product which has an impact on how you aprehend your world.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Social aspect&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One aspect I missed as a student was the richness of this world.&lt;br /&gt;
While studying, I enjoyed reading books and doing homework but this was only the tip of the iceberg.&lt;br /&gt;
I didn't take advantage of the networking aspect.&lt;br /&gt;
For instance I only discovered the concepts of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hackathon," title="hackathon"&gt;hackathon&lt;/a&gt; and meetup not so long ago.&lt;br /&gt;
I regret not being aware of these events earlier.&lt;br /&gt;
Fortunaltely, throughout my young carrer I met people who showed me how socializing the programming world can be.&lt;br /&gt;
Now aware of it I changed my approach of being a developer.&lt;br /&gt;
Today I'm proactive. I read more blogs, I have my own blog, I participate to open source projects, I try to help fellow programmers, I ask help to fellow programmers, I try new things and share things. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Try , share and propose&lt;/strong&gt; are the new watchwords, and that is for the best.
Among people who inspired me, two have a special place. &lt;br /&gt;
They proved me that, &lt;strong&gt;as a developer, you can not only be an internal asset but also an ambassador for a company&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
That is to say, you can be a &lt;strong&gt;dev evangelist&lt;/strong&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Dev evangelist&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Who is he ?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November 2013 I met &lt;a href="http://timgrid.com/" title="Tim's blog"&gt;Tim Fall&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://nicholasquinlan.com/" title="Nick's blog"&gt;Nick Quilan&lt;/a&gt; two dev evangelists from SendGrid.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;So what is a dev evangelist ?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
You can raise your eyebrows when reading the word "evangelist". Why such a religious word is associated to the term of developer ?
Obviously it's a metaphor.&lt;br /&gt;
Evangelism is the act of relying information about a particular set of beliefs to others with intention of conversion.&lt;br /&gt;
Where I come from, "evangelist" has a strong conotation. Something you will not/should not associate with a term like developer.&lt;br /&gt;
So to speak to everyone, let's consider titles such as &lt;strong&gt;technical advocate&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;technical ambasador&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
As a developer he/she contributes to software products but stresses on the social and community aspect.&lt;br /&gt;
Not only he/she codes, he/she is also the ambassador of an entire company.&lt;br /&gt;
- He presents products and features he directly contributed to (such as SDKs, APIs, articles...).&lt;br /&gt;
- He writes articles and tutorials to help the community he is devoted to.&lt;br /&gt;
- He helps to design products and develops businesses. &lt;br /&gt;
More importantly, &lt;strong&gt;he is here to help&lt;/strong&gt;, and this aspect appeals to me a lot.&lt;br /&gt;
In the rest of the article we will refer to dev evangelist as DE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why do they matter ?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Being well rounded in both communication and technical skills&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In France, we do not have this culture of DE (I don't know any french group using this concept, if you do let me know). &lt;br /&gt;
We usually let commercials do the presentation part, and programmers the technical part.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Things are separated&lt;/strong&gt;.  This matter of fact is not exclusive to the software world.&lt;br /&gt;
But this strategy has a major flaw. Commercials, no matter how good they are, usually &lt;strong&gt;do not have the technical knowledge&lt;/strong&gt; not only to sell a product but also to explain it from a technical view and even to contribute to it. &lt;br /&gt;
I met commercials who previously were developers and now promote softwares. But they completly changed their job.&lt;br /&gt;
They don't code anymore, and it's only a matter of time before their technical skills start to dwindle.&lt;br /&gt;
They cannot feel how a software or an API is perceived by the community it is conceived for.&lt;br /&gt;
And one cannot expect programmers to deeply understand the need of their end users if they do not interact with them.&lt;br /&gt;
I noticed this symptom during the API days in Paris.&lt;br /&gt;
On the one hand, we had two commercials. On the other, one DE from Sengrid. Both groups presented tools related to APIs.&lt;br /&gt;
The first were clumsy in their approach as they clearly didn't prepared their presentation and heavily relied on their slides.&lt;br /&gt;
Yet the presented tool was something powerful and apealing (generate an API based on HTML elements of any websites).&lt;br /&gt;
But they did not transfer any enthiusasm to the audience and let them guess what was behind the product. &lt;br /&gt;
On the other hand, the DE was full of inspiration and enthusiasm, and made it contagious. Slides were not so important as he was able to mesmerize the audience.&lt;br /&gt;
In the end I was full of ideas and motivation to explore the API he contributes to and the business behind it.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One can ask the following question. &lt;strong&gt;Why not associate a commercial with a programmer?&lt;/strong&gt; 
That's what happened during the APIdays' hackathon.&lt;br /&gt;
Among the presentators, one commercial and one programmer paired together. The association may sound good.
Indeed,  if a commercial does not fit the technical part, let's associate a programmer to leverage interaction with the audience.&lt;br /&gt;
But the programmer simply didn't want to be here. He presented the tool he contributed to and then left.&lt;br /&gt;
That was dubious. On the one hand a commercial was speaking about what was being done by the programmer. On the other hand a silent guy was hardly explaining what was happening and left when everything was done.&lt;br /&gt;
Why did this association didn't perform as one can expect ? Why this lack of motivation while all the other DE were making their show ?&lt;br /&gt;
Two reasons come to my mind.&lt;br /&gt;
1. &lt;strong&gt;the job&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It was saturday morning and the programmer was doing extra. In other word he wasn't paid.
To make things simple every non DE didn't stay more than half a day during this two days long event.&lt;br /&gt;
On the contrary, working on non predifined shedules is part of the job of DE. He is devoted to a community, which still exists during the weekend.&lt;br /&gt;
2. &lt;strong&gt;skills&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
DE besides being good developers and fast learners are inclined to socialize with people. Express ideas and make them simple. 
In france we don't have jobs specially fitted to speak for developers. We usually send pure developers, but they do not necessarily fit the task although they may be very good at developping.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Being open minded&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading this, one can say that DEs are new breed of commercials.
In my point of view, &lt;strong&gt;they are not.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;In fact they aim at a different target, that is to say developers&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
While commercials aim at companies, decision makers and share olders, dev evangelists are &lt;strong&gt;programmers who speak to programmers&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
Looking for business oppurtunities is part of their job, but their main goal is to help people. No matter what they are working on. &lt;br /&gt;
If it concerns the API they contribute to, it's fine. If it's not, it's also fine. &lt;br /&gt;
They also represent a state of mind (and skills) of their employer. 
Nick Fall once told me the following story:   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During an hackathon, one DE proposed to help a team. &lt;br /&gt;
Knowing he was working for Sendgrid they politely declined his help saying that they didn't need to send emails with their application.&lt;br /&gt;
He insisted and made it to succesfully help the team. Later, one team's member heard about sendgrid at his job. 
He was asked about sendgrid's products and replied this: "&lt;em&gt;I don't know anything about sendgrid but given the level of skill of their developers, I don't think their products are bad.&lt;/em&gt;"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tell-tale story sums up pretty well what a dev evangelist is devoted to.
As I was intrigued by the way you become a DE, I asked Tim on how to become a dev evangelist, and I will finish with his simple answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"&lt;strong&gt;The best way to be a dev evangelist is to be a dev evangelist.&lt;/strong&gt;"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Am I happy to be developer ? Yes.&lt;br /&gt;
Altough we do not have (yet) the attractiveness of other carrers like physician or pilot, I'm conviced that things are changing for the better.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Jobs like dev evangelist, to me, are the evidence of a mutation in the programming world.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
It proves that being a developper is far from the cliche vehiculed by medias such as movies and are real asset for companies.&lt;br /&gt;
Will I be still a developer in 10 years ? Well I don't know. I also have other passions I can dive into like movies, photos or travels. &lt;br /&gt;
But being a programmer gives me the oppurtunity to meet interesting people and think on various topics.&lt;br /&gt;
The era in which we live gives more and more place to technology.&lt;br /&gt;
This trend won't change (&lt;a href="http://www.theguardian.com/environment/earth-insight/2014/mar/14/nasa-civilisation-irreversible-collapse-study-scientists"&gt;at least for the 15 next years&lt;/a&gt;) and this is good news for developers.  &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="carreer"></category><category term="technologies"></category></entry><entry><title>Pourquoi le livre electronique compte</title><link href="/pourquoi-le-livre-electronique-compte.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-06-22T16:59:00+02:00</published><author><name>ihommmani</name></author><id>tag:,2014-06-22:pourquoi-le-livre-electronique-compte.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Pourquoi ai-je choisi le livre électronique ?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="eBook" src="/images/book.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Le plaisir de lire&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La lecture est pour moi un plaisir que je partage avec de nombreuse personnes.&lt;br /&gt;
Je ne vais pas ici énumérer les bienfaits de cette activité mais plutôt m'intéresser sur les vecteurs par lesquels elle se fait.&lt;br /&gt;
Je les partage en deux catégories:&lt;br /&gt;
1. &lt;strong&gt;Le numérique&lt;/strong&gt; (ordinateur, tablette, livre électronique) 
2.  &lt;strong&gt;Le digital&lt;/strong&gt; (papier).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Je suis un consommateur de livre sur format numérique et plus précisément sur &lt;strong&gt;livre éléctronique&lt;/strong&gt;.
Ce dernier fait néanmoins apparaître de nombreuses réticences parmi les lecteurs de livres papier. &lt;br /&gt;
Les arguments avancés sont plus ou moins les mêmes.&lt;br /&gt;
Je vais m'attacher à les analyser et vous fournir ma vision des choses en tant qu'utilisateur assidu du livre électronique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;L'argument financier&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cet argument consiste à avancer &lt;strong&gt;le prix "élevé" des eBooks&lt;/strong&gt; (ne pas comprendre le support mais bien le livre en format electronique).&lt;br /&gt;
Elevé par rapport au prix qu'aurait souhaité le client. &lt;br /&gt;
Il n'est pas rare de tomber sur  un tel qui dénonce un vol voir milite pour une quasi gratuité du format électronique. &lt;br /&gt;
Mais pourquoi donc ? &lt;strong&gt;Pour la simple et mauvaise raison que le format électronique est dématérialisé&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;br /&gt;
Or si le livre ne nécessite pas de coût de fabrication ou qu'en tout cas qu'il devienne dérisoire, il est tout à fait normal que le prix baisse considérablement. CQFD
La réalité est comme souvent un peu plus complexe.&lt;br /&gt;
Cet argument repose sur une prémice non dite mais implicite : &lt;em&gt;Une grande parti du prix du livre réside dans son coût de fabrication&lt;/em&gt;.
Ce qu'il y a de plus précieux ou coûteux dans un livre serait donc le papier sur lequel on l'imprime ? &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Que devient le travail intellectuel des auteurs&lt;/strong&gt; ? &lt;strong&gt;Le travail de recherche et la prise de risque des maisons d'éditions&lt;/strong&gt; ?&lt;br /&gt;
Quoi qu'il en soit il y a un fait indéniable: &lt;strong&gt;le format electronique est systématiquement moins cher que le format papier neuf&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
Autre fait important à avoir en tête. Le code de la propriété intelectuelle français garantit un passage dans le domaine publique d'une oeuvre 70 ans 
après la mort de son auteur. &lt;br /&gt;
Concrètement cela veut dire qu'une myriade de classiques est &lt;strong&gt;librement disponible&lt;/strong&gt; sur les différentes plateformes de téléchargements d'Ebooks.&lt;br /&gt;
Le &lt;em&gt;compte de Monte Cristo&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;les Misérables&lt;/em&gt;... sont autant de classiques gratuitement téléchargeables. &lt;br /&gt;
J'en suis un bénéficiaire, car la plupart de ces oeuvres m'ont intimidées étant plus jeune, soit par leur taille soit par leur complexité. &lt;br /&gt;
Aujourd'hui je suis content de pouvoir parler d'Edmond Dantes, de Jean Valjean et d'autres encore. &lt;br /&gt;
L'ebook, au delà de l'avantage financier, permet de découvrir ou de redécouvrir des oeuvres qui pour certaines seraient restées de vagues titres entendus au détour d'un cours de français.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;L'argument "Big brother is watching you"&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;L'émergence d'une société de l'information et de la communication rend de plus en plus prégnant l'exigence de la protection des donnés personnelles et plus généralement de la vie privée. &lt;br /&gt;
Les détracteurs du livre éléctronique n'ont pas oublié de le noter tant ils mettent en avant le manque de transparence de la gestion des livres par la plateforme d'achat. (un &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/07/18/technology/companies/18amazon.html?_r=0" title="Big brother"&gt;précédent douteux&lt;/a&gt; plaide en leur faveur) &lt;br /&gt;
Mais quel est réellement ce manque de transparence cher à certaine personne ? &lt;br /&gt;
Il faut savoir que &lt;strong&gt;la loi Européenne protège le consommateur de certaines dérives des géants du Web&lt;/strong&gt;.
Afin de protéger le droit à la vie privée, à l'égard du traitement automatisé des données personnelles, le Conseil de l'Europe a élaboré la "Convention pour la protection des personnes à l'égard du traitement automatisé des données à caractère personnel".&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.conventions.coe.int/Treaty/FR/Treaties/Html/108.htm" title="convention"&gt;lien&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On peut très bien en rire en disant que ces conditions ne valent que pour ceux qui veulent bien y croire.&lt;br /&gt;
Il n'empêche qu'&lt;strong&gt;un cadre légal est bien définit&lt;/strong&gt;.
Cela dit on peut très bien "cacher" les livres que l'on possède en se coupant totalement de l'internet. Je serais tout de même curieux de connaitre les moteurs de recherche qu'utilisent ces personnes ainsi que leur serveur de mail... &lt;br /&gt;
Cela étant-dit, &lt;strong&gt;que critique-t-on réélement lorsque l'on pointe les risques de dérive lié à l'achat de livre éléctronique ?&lt;/strong&gt;
Le support ou les acteurs des plateformes de téléchargement ? &lt;br /&gt;
L'ebook n'est en rien responsable de cette situation. Lorsque quelqu'un commet un crime, on ne juge pas l'arme du crime mais bien l'auteur des faits (j'ai quand même l'exemple du taser en tête mais cela reste des cas minoritaire).&lt;br /&gt;
Ne jugeons donc pas le livre électronique en tant que responsable de certaines dérives.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;L'argument de celui qui n'a rien compris&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Il arrive de temps en temps d'entendre, "&lt;em&gt;A quoi me servirait un livre electronique puisque je peux déjà lire sur ma tablette&lt;/em&gt;".  &lt;br /&gt;
L'argument est faible. Peut on penser ne pas acheter de chaussures de sport pour la seule raison que l'on possède déjà des chaussures de marche ?&lt;br /&gt;
Ne pas acheter de VTT pour un treck en montagne parce que l'on possède déjà notre mono pignon pour déambuler dans les rues ?
&lt;strong&gt;Lire sur une tablette n'a rien d'un plaisir&lt;/strong&gt;. La luminosité est similaire à celle d'un écran d'ordinateur. Je ne sais pas pour vous mais je n'aurais jamais l'idée de lire &lt;em&gt;A la recherche du temps perdu&lt;/em&gt; sur un écran d'ordinateur et à fortiori sur une tablette. &lt;br /&gt;
Assez ironiquement c'est un des livres qui m'a été offert avec la Nexus 7... &lt;br /&gt;
Non, la tablette est adaptée à la lecture d'un certain contenu type article de journaux, page web voire pdf.&lt;br /&gt;
A l'inverse &lt;strong&gt;le rendu d'un livre électronique se veut très proche de celui du papier&lt;/strong&gt;. Pas de luminosité et avec ça la possibilité d'accéder à tout moment à un dictionnaire (très pratique dans le cas de lecture en langues étrangères) et de régler la taille de la police (pratique pour les personnes ayant des problèmes de vue).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;L'argument sentimental&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Je parle d'argument mais en fait il ne suis en rien la logique de l'argumentation.&lt;br /&gt;
Il ne se base sur rien de tangible ni de concret. &lt;br /&gt;
C'est le fameux " &lt;em&gt;Y a un truc en plus avec le papier, que je ne ressent pas avec le livre électronique.&lt;/em&gt;"
Ce qui est plutôt comique, c'est que la plupart des personnes m'ayant avancé cet argument n'avait jamais essayé (ou si peu) le livre électronique.  &lt;br /&gt;
J'accepte bien la critique mais encore faut-il qu'elle soit fondée.&lt;br /&gt;
On peut apprecier que les livres prennent la poussière dans une bibliothèque ou l'odeur du papier jaunit. En soi ce n'est pas incompatible avec l'achat d'un livre électronique. &lt;br /&gt;
Parce que oui il y a des choses en plus avec le format papier. &lt;br /&gt;
En premier lieu le poids. Ensuite la place que prenne des livre dans une bibliothèque. Certaine personne les revendent voire les donne mais je ne pense pas qu'ils soient majoritaires. &lt;br /&gt;
Les livres de poches n'ont parfois de poche que le nom. Avec un livre electronique peu importe le nombre de page, le nombre de livre, le nombre de Bd, il tiendra toujours dans ma poche pour un poid équivalent à celui d'une nouvelle d'Edgard Poe. &lt;br /&gt;
Le format restera toujours le même. &lt;br /&gt;
Lire d'une seule main est un luxe non négligeable, surtout lors des heures de pointe dans les transport en commun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pour être tout à fait honnête il m'arrive d'acheter des livres papier. Tout simplement parce que &lt;strong&gt;le livre électronique n'apporte pas de réponse aux défauts du format papier dans sa globalité&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
Il ne peut même pas prétendre à remplacer certaines catégories.&lt;br /&gt;
En premier lieux les livres elctroniques ne reproduisent pas pour le moment la couleur. Elément au combien fondamental dans la litérature enfantine par exemple. Des livres comme &lt;a href="http://lireauxenfants.com/livres-elmer.html" title="Elemere"&gt;Elmere l'éléphant&lt;/a&gt; pedraient tout leur sens.  &lt;br /&gt;
De même, pour une question de format, je considère que les livres de tables auront toujours leur place dans une bibliothèque tout autant que les livres illustrés. &lt;br /&gt;
Ils occupent une part importante dans l'enfance. Le touché est fondamentale à cet age. 
Enfin certains livre ne sont pas et ne seront pas édité au format électronique. Trop ancien ou tout simplement hors du circuit d'édition.  &lt;br /&gt;
Le format papier apparait alors comme l'unique alternative.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J'ai essayé le long de cet article d'exprimer mon ressenti face à une peur non fondée. Celle de voir disparaitre le format papier au profit du format électronique. Le format électronique est un progrès sur de nombreux aspect de la lecture. &lt;br /&gt;
Il n'a néanmoins pas vocation à faire disparaitre le format papier mais plutot à le compléter voire le faire évoluer.
Ne soyons pas timorés et disons oui à l'évolution de la lecture.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Je finirais cet article par un extrait issu de Gargantua de François Rabelais.
« C'est pourquoi fault ouvrir le livre et soigneusement peser ce que y est déduict. [...] Puis, par curieuse leçon et meditation frequente, rompre l'os, et sugcer la substantifique moelle, [...]. »
Cessons d'accorder de l'importance au format. Fut-il papier ou electronique l'important est bien la &lt;strong&gt;substantique moelle&lt;/strong&gt;.  &lt;br /&gt;
J'y ajouterais enfin qu'il faut savoir vivre avec son temps.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="ebooks"></category></entry></feed>